What? It disappeared.
So what happened yesterday? I don't know, he didn't think so, I
mean he didn't say anything, the רבי Rebbe didn't tell me. All
right, בוקר טוב Boker Tov again. We're in מסכת מכות Masechet Makkot
in the second chapter, אלו הן הגולין, Elu Hen HaGolin, so we're
talking about people that are being exiled for mistakenly killing somebody. We're
in דף ח Daf Chet in sort of in the middle in
the משנה Mishnah that starts four lines from the wide lines on
the דף. Daf. מתניתין: Matnitin: האב גולה על ידי הבן והבן גולה
על ידי האב הכל גולין על ידי ישראל וישראל גולין על ידיהן
חוץ מגר תושב וגר תושב אינו גולה אלא על ידי גר תושב.
Ha'av goleh al yedei haben vehaben goleh al yedei ha'av hakol golin
al yedei yisrael veyisrael golin al yedeihen chutz miger toshav veger toshav
eino goleh ela al yedei ger toshav.
The father gets exiled for his unintentional murder of his son, the
son gets exiled for his unintentional murder of the father, everyone and
here is a list of everyone and we'll unpack them in just
a minute, everyone gets exiled for killing a ישראל, Yisrael, and ישראל,
Yisrael, a Jew, gets exiled for killing someone else except if they
kill a גר תושב. Ger Toshav. And the גר תושב Ger Toshav
does not get exiled unless he is involved in the murder of
another גר תושב. Ger Toshav. The גר תושב Ger Toshav is someone
who is not Jewish but fulfilling the seven נוח, Noach, the נוחאידס.
Noachites. The עובד כוכבים Oved Kochavim is someone who's not Jewish, not
fulfilling anything, and עבד כנעני Eved Kenaani is a servant of a
Jewish person who is a Canaanite but lives with the Jews. There's
going to be three different categories and ישראל. Yisrael. Some questions that
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask about the משנה, Mishnah, if
we had time it would be great to try to guess them,
but the issue that the משנה Mishnah singles out: the father and
the son. What difference does it make for a father and son?
It says that ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon if they kill somebody
unintentionally they get exiled. Why did the משנה Mishnah opt to list
up the father and the son? The גמרא Gemara is going to
try to unpack it and then the issue of who's הכל גולין
על ידי ישראל Hakol golin al yedei Yisrael and how do we
exclude any one of them based on what? Yes, questions coming. Okay.
There's a lot to unpack and we're a little behind and there's
interesting stories at the bottom of ט Tet and in the back,
the ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat, so I'm going to try to make
it there. There's complex conversations, we'll try not to completely get bogged
down and just read along. Okay, גמרא Gemara says: האב גולה על
ידי הבן. Ha'av goleh al yedei haben. The גמרא Gemara asks a
question now about the משנה, Mishnah, we're on ח Chet in the
middle. והאמרת יצא האב המכה את בנו? Veha'amart yatza ha'av hamakeh et
bno?
So you just told me that the father is going to get
exiled because of on account of his unintentional murder of his son,
but earlier you told me that a father when if he hits
his son and unintentionally kills him that he's going to be יצא?
yatza? So which specific case are we talking about? Of course, needless
to say, all stuff that is probably hard for us to deal
with in our modern approach to education, but let's just see it
in the time and in the גמרא Gemara instead of trying to
deal with the values that are being expressed. It also, if he
were to kill his son. Welcome
heat. Yeah, he could kill his son in other ways besides by
giving him
punishment, the axe or any other of these things. Right, right.
And this is part of what the גמרא Gemara wants to understand.
What is the case that this is trying to exclude? If it's
unintentional and it's like a regular case, then
it's unintentional. What is the specific of the father of a son
that the גמרא Gemara is trying to lift? So the answer it
gives us: דגמיר. Degamir. What is דגמיר? Degamir? This is a word
we should know, right? גמרא Gemara is like learning. So this is
while teaching. But you said, no, it said דגמיר, Degamir, this is
somebody who's already learned. והאמרת אף על גב דגמיר מצוה קעביד? Veha'amart
af al gav degamir mitzvah ka'avid? בשוליא דנגרי. Beshulya deNagrai. So now
we're not talking about teaching the son תורה, Torah, we're talking about
teaching the son a profession like שוליא דנגרי, shulya deNagrai, like assistant
of a carpenter. So that doesn't count as תורה, Torah, therefore we
have to make an exception. The גמרא Gemara challenges it. It says
שוליא דנגרי חיותא היא דלמדיה. Shulya deNagrai chayuta hee delamdei. Like you
also have to teach your child a profession, right,
elsewhere we have to... We have a פסוק pasuk that says וראה
חיים עם האשה אשר אהבת. Ur'eh chayim im ha-ishah asher ahavta. You
should see life, you should have a life, you should have a
living, a profession that you can live from. שוליא דנגרא Shulya de-nagra
counts too. But no, in this case we're trying to exclude the
situation of a גמיר gamir of somebody who's already learned in both
תורה Torah and professional life, but the father's teaching him אומנותא אחריתא.
umanuta achrita.
Going back to the משנה Mishnah and lifting up the next section
of the משנה, Mishnah, והבן גולה על ידי האב. ve-haben goleh al
yedei ha-av. The גמרא Gemara is challenging it, ורמינהי. u-remini. We already
have a thing that says מכה נפש, makeh nefesh, if somebody kills
somebody, then they would be exiled, right? If somebody kills someone else
unintentionally, there would be exile to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. And
there's an exclusion to that, פרט למכה אביו. prat le-makeh aviv. Somebody
who kills his father does not get exile, gets a more severe
punishment. רב כהנא Rav Kahana is trying to settle it. אמר רב
כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא רבי שמעון והא
רבנן. ha Rabbi Shimon ve-ha rabbanan. If you remember from סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon had a different ladder for the punishments than
רבנן. rabbanan. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said to us that חנק, chenek,
I believe, no, שרפה sreifah was more severe than
סקילה. skilah. Burning was more severe than stoning, choking, strangulation was more
severe than killing someone with a sword. The rabbis said slightly different.
סקילה Skilah is more severe than שרפה, sreifah, סייף sayaf is more
severe than חנק. chenek. Do we need to write it down or
moving on?
Based on what we think is more severe, some of these things
can be atoned by an exile and some of these things cannot.
Depending on how you have the ladder, that is going to impact
how you unpack it. הא רבי שמעון והא רבנן. ha Rabbi Shimon
ve-ha rabbanan. ורבי שמעון דאמר חנק חמור מסייף, ve-Rabbi Shimon de-amar chenek
chamur mi-sayaf, שגגת סייף ניתנה לכפרה, shigagat sayaf nitnah le-chaparah, שגגת חנק
לא ניתנה לכפרה. shigagat chenek lo nitnah le-chaparah.
For רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, for whom strangulation is more severe
than killing somebody with a sword, the sword can be atoned for
with כפרה, kaparah, i.e. exile, and strangulation cannot because this is higher
up. But the rabbis? Why can't anything be atoned for? Because there
is an exclusion for what can be atoned with exile and what
can't. Based on what? Based on פסוקים pesukim and based on... this
is the first time we're seeing that concept. Until now, the exile
was just based on, was it an accident, how intentional was the
act that resulted in the death? Now we're looking at with what
the death? This is רב כהנא Rav Kahana trying to settle the
fact that the בן גולה על ידי האב ben goleh al yedei
ha-av is something that the משנה Mishnah is specifying. That's our train
of thought. We don't know yet that that's how it's going to
go, but that's his offer.
Why is the משנה Mishnah specifying א בן גולה על ידי האב?
a ben goleh al yedei ha-av? Should be that everyone who kills
somebody unintentionally gets exile. Apparently, we specify the אב av and the
בן, ben, therefore there must be something special about them. We don't
yet know what it is. רב כהנא Rav Kahana offers to us
the idea that maybe it has to do with the degree of
punishments. לרבנן דאמרי סייף חמור מחנק, le-rabbanan de-amri sayaf chamur mi-chenek, הורג
אביו בשוגג שגגת סייף. horeg aviv be-shogeg shigagat sayaf.
For the rabbis, they compare killing a father by the son to
a שגגת סייף, shigagat sayaf, to the murder with a sword. ושגגת
סייף ניתנה לכפרה. ve-shigagat sayaf nitnah le-chaparah. Do they ever agree what
the punishment for killing a father is?
Do they agree? It's just a question of what happens if you
do it unintentionally.
If it's intentional, then it's a murder. So then no, but then
how do you get killed? You get killed by who gets killed?
The person that kills the son and whoever it is. Wait, I
thought you said beheading. The son killed the father. Strangulation, is that
it? I mean, I guess first that part if it's intentional, but
unintentional? Because they were just saying one is חמור chamur than the
other, that you might be able to get גלות galut for based
on a reason we don't know why. And we talked about back
in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, we talked about what does this חמור chamur mean?
We're not sure what does this חמור chamur mean. It could be
the intentionality, not necessarily that this is something worse. They're anyway dead.
But the point is that if you align them in the way
of the רבנן, rabbanan, then the person can get כפרה kaparah and
if you align them in the way of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
then the person, the son cannot get כפרה. kaparah. Oh wait, but
it's really
not... So it seems like both, what do you mean by punishment?
Not by punishment, by their execution, means of execution. In other words,
if it's intentional he has to get the more severe form of
execution. If it's unintentional, he can, exile will atone. It's assumed that
it is
unintentional, right? Because that's what we're dealing with, we're dealing with the
עיר מקלט, ir miklat, the עיר מקלט ir miklat is only for
unintentional murder.
The trying to settle this,
I don't know if going to the end of this piece is
going to help, but it says an unintentional commission of a crime
subject to the beheading is given to atone through exile. Right, that's
what I'm saying. So that's why if he can get the beheading
then he can get exile,
he can be atoned. Inadvertent, you follow me? The question is you
think of the beheading as a punishment to the son had it
been intentional? No, no, I don't think so. No, what I'm saying
is it says here, the unintentional commission of a crime that can
be punished by the beheading, okay, which the רבנן Rabanan is saying,
okay, but not רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
saying it the other way around. That's why you can't give them
exile. Right, according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the son cannot get
exile, according to the רבנן Rabanan he can get exile.
Okay. Alright. But we still don't know why, in other words, why
because it's חנק chenek or because it's סייף sayif he can be
atoned for versus he can't be atoned for. I mean it seems
a little bit arbitrary. It could be. I mean there's a lot
of things about this chapter we've seen earlier that are like גזירת
הכתוב, gezeirat hakatuv, the עיר מקלט ir miklat are also גזירת הכתוב
gezeirat hakatuv and this whole thing is also going to be like
how do we exactly break the categories of who gets which punishment.
So
I'm not sure we completely unpacked it but I can't stay there,
so we'll just move on. Okay. רבא Rava is trying to explain
it differently. He says, פרט לעושה חבורה באביו בשוגג. perat la'oseh chavurah
be'aviv beshogeg. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka datach amina, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka
datach amina, כיון דבמזיד בר קטלא הוא, kevan demavizid bar katla hu,
בשוגג נמי ליגלי, beshogeg nami ligli, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
that's
not. Okay, so רבא Rava is trying to explain it.
A son specifically. Do you want to share it so that... No,
I'll just say, okay, I don't want to interrupt. No, no, just
say. ערוך לנר, Aruch Lener,
he says it's still a verse is needed because the logic on
its own is not compelling. Which is what I was saying. That's
what we were saying, it's called גזירת הכתוב, gezeirat hakatuv,
that's how it is, we can only go so far.
Okay. רבא Rava is trying to offer something else that when a
son kills the father there's actually two transgressions. He had to beat
him and he had to kill him. So he had to do,
make a חבורה chavurah and so like there's more of an intentionality
here. And if במזיד bemezid he would be בר קטלא bar katla
and בשוגג beshogeg he could be exiled. And therefore this case is
brought to us with the son who is the משנה Mishna tells
us specifically the son is גולה. goleh. Okay. הכל גולין על ידי
ישראל. Hakol golin al yedei Yisrael.
Who is this group of הכל? hakol? הכל גולין על ידי ישראל,
Hakol golin al yedei Yisrael, לאיתויי מאי? le'ituyei mai? Who are we
trying to add? לאיתויי עבד וכותי, Le'ituyei eved ve'Kuti,
a Canaanite servant and the Samaritan, the כותים. Kutim.
Okay. ותנינא, Vetenina, ברייתא, braita, להא דתנו רבנן, leha detanu rabanan, עבד
וכותי גולה ולוקה על ידי ישראל, eved ve'Kuti goleh velokeh al yedei
Yisrael, וישראל גולה ולוקה על ידי כותי ועבד. ve'Yisrael goleh velokeh al
yedei Kuti ve'eved. So
understanding is that a Canaanite servant and a Samaritan, the כותי,
Kuti, are exiled if by the account of an unintentional murder of
a Jew, and likewise they get
lashes, they're flogged, right, by a Jew. And the Israel likewise gets
exiled and gets lashes for on the account of a כותי Kuti
and a עבד כנעני. eved Kena'ani. Okay. Trying to undo this. בשלמא
עבד וכותי גולה על ידי ישראל ולוקה, Bishlama eved ve'Kuti goleh al
yedei Yisrael velokeh, גולה דקטליה Goleh de'katlei ולוקה דלטייה. velokeh de'lateih.
So
he gets, what is the distinction between the גלות galut and the
lashes? He's going to be exiled for killing somebody and he's going
to be getting lashes for cursing somebody. Wait. This is unclear and
we're going to see that the lines there are very, very fuzzy,
especially with the גר תושב. ger toshav. אלא ישראל גולה ולוקה על
ידי כותי. Ella Yisrael goleh v'lokeh al yedei Kuti. בשלמא גולה דקטליה.
Bishlama goleh d'katlya.
Okay, fine, we got it. A Jew is going to get exiled
and lashes on the account of hurting a
כותי, Kuti, Samaritan or a non-Jew. Okay, so we got it. בשלמא
גולה דקטליה. Bishlama goleh d'katlya. He gets exiled for killing somebody mistakenly.
But לוקה אלא לוקה אמאי דלטיה? Lokeh ella lokeh amai d'latya? What,
like we're going to give lashes to the Jew for cursing
another non-Jew? הפסוק Hapasuk tells us ונשיא בעמך לא תאור, v'nasi b'amcha
lo ta'or, a prince or a leader in your people you will
not curse. That should be the עושה מעשה עמך, oseh ma'aseh amcha,
with somebody that is actually part of your people and not part
of another nation. So what, what is exactly this case? This case
does not quite pan out when the משנה mishna says הכל. hakol.
Do you want to add something? Because... you sure? Okay. So
רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov is going to try
to unpack it in a slightly different way. He says כגון שהעיד
בו והוזם. kegon she'eid bo v'huzam. So
maybe somebody gave a false testimony and he became an עד זומם,
ed zomem, and therefore he gets the punishment of, remember the whole
עדים זוממים? edim zomemim? So he now gets the punishment of the
person who was on the stand against whom he's testifying. דכוותיה גבי
עבד שהעיד בו והוזם. D'kvateih gabi eved she'eid bo v'huzam.
So now it's a again there's a question on a question. Wait,
we're talking about a עבד, eved, a servant, who gave a testimony
and was, there was a הזמה hazama against him, right? The עבד
eved gave a false testimony and he was הוזם. huzam. But the
גמרא gemara is immediately asking עבד בר עדות הוא? eved bar edut
hu? What, wait, you mean a servant can testify? That also does
not make sense. אלא אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא הכא במאי
עסקינן. Ella amar Rav Acha bireih d'Rav Ika hacha b'mai askinan. What
is it that we're actually talking about? We're talking about a specific
case כגון שהכהו
הכאה שאין בה
שוה פרוטה. kegon shehikahu haka'ah she'ein bah shaveh prutah. He beat him,
slogged him with, in the case where one was struck in a
blow that is not like worth anything, is not, doesn't have the
capacity to cause damage that is even worth one פרוטה. prutah. דאמר
רב אמי אמר רבי יוחנן הכהו הכאה שאין בה שוה פרוטה לוקה
ולא מקשינן הכאה לקללה. D'amar Rav Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan hikahu haka'ah
she'ein bah shaveh prutah lokeh v'lo makshinan haka'ah l'klalah. So
wait,
Rav Ami says that Rav Yochanan says although one who strikes another
pays damages and is not flogged, if he struck him with a
blow that does not have the capacity to cause damage worth even
one פרוטה, prutah, since there is no payment, then he gets lashes
for violating a Torah prohibition. Okay, not sure if
we've completely unpacked it but we're just going to have to live
with it. Questions? No questions. Okay. Okay,
going back to the משנה. mishna. חוץ מעל ידי גר תושב Chutz
me'al yedei ger toshav etc.
So now we have a big problem with this פסוק pasuk and
with this statement by the משנה. mishna. And actually some commentaries think
that this is
copied incorrectly, that it's not, should not say חוץ מעל ידי גר
תושב, chutz me'al yedei ger toshav, but it should say חוץ מגר
תושב. chutz m'ger toshav. Cause is it caused by the גר תושב
ger toshav or is it done to the גר תושב? ger toshav?
Okay, unclear. רגע. Rega.
Okay,
so everyone is exiled
for their unintentional murder of a Jew, and a Jew is exiled
due to all of them except for when it is due to
a גר תושב. ger toshav. And we specified the גר תושב ger
toshav being somebody who lives in the land
and fulfills the seven נחיידס, Nochides, but is not, is not a
Jew. אלמא גר תושב עובד כוכבים הוא. Alma ger toshav oved kochavim
hu. So now we have a very complex conversation on is the
גר תושב ger toshav the same status like the עובד כוכבים? oved
kochavim? Is it the same? Is it the same as the non-Jew
who did not accept the נחיידס Nochides or is he a different...
a different status? Okay.
The גמרא Gemara comments, let's go back. אלמא גר תושב עובד כוכבים
הוא. Alma ger toshav oved kochavim hu. אימא סיפא גר תושב גולה
על ידי גר תושב. Ima seifa ger toshav goleh al yedei ger
toshav.
So see, if you give him גלות, galut, then he's like a
Jew because the ערי מקלט arei miklat were given, and we'll see
two conflicting פסוקים pesukim coming up in just a second. The
ערי מקלט arei miklat were given to the Jews to have a
place of escape in case of an unintentional murder. So now, is
the גר תושב ger toshav in this category of a non-Jew or
is the גר תושב ger toshav in the category of a ישראל?
Yisrael? And we see that we have two conflicting פסוקים pesukim and
therefore we're trying to figure out if the גר תושב ger toshav
is the one killed or the one being killed. Okay.
רב כהנא Rav Kahana is trying to settle it in the following
way. אמר רב כהנא: Amar Rav Kahana: לא קשיא, lo kashya, כאן
בגר תושב שהרג גר תושב, kan be-ger toshav she-harag ger toshav, כאן
בגר תושב שהרג ישראל. kan be-ger toshav she-harag Yisrael. So he's trying
to say that the case of a גר תושב ger toshav who
is given the privilege of escaping to the עיר מקלט ir miklat
is because he killed another גר תושב. ger toshav. As a resident
of the land, he's also eligible for the ערי מקלט. arei miklat.
But if he kills another ישראל, Yisrael, then he cannot be atoned
through exile and he's going to get the death penalty.
איכא דרמי קראי אהדדי. Ika derami karai ahadadei. So there's also a
way to understand the same thing that we just explained from two
פסוקים pesukim in במדבר Bamidbar and this is what I referred to.
לבני ישראל ולגר ולתושב בתוכם תהיינה שש הערים. Livnei Yisrael vela-ger vela-toshav
betocham tihyena sheish ha-arim.
So there's one פסוק pasuk in במדבר Bamidbar 35:15 that says that
the ערי מקלט arei miklat are going to be for the children
of Israel and for the גר ger and for the תושב, toshav,
again a distinction as opposed to calling him
a גר תושב, ger toshav, לגר ולתושב, la-ger vela-toshav, we saw it
with אברהם Avraham last week's פרשה parsha when he says גר ותושב
אנכי. ger ve-toshav anochi. Okay. And in
במדבר Bamidbar 35:12, it says והיו לכם הערים למקלט. vehayu lachem ha-arim
lemiklat. לכם ולא לגרים. Lachem velo lagerim. So which way is it?
In one פסוק pasuk it says the ערי מקלט arei miklat is
for you and for the גר ger and for the תושב, toshav,
so like for everybody in the land, but in another פסוק pasuk
it says והיו לכם, vehayu lachem, so it's only to you. רב
כהנא Rav Kahana says again not a problem. גר תושב שהרג ישראל,
Ger toshav she-harag Yisrael, גר תושב
שהרג גר תושב ger toshav she-harag ger toshav get different—one can atone
and one cannot atone. If he kills a ישראל, Yisrael, a Jew,
he cannot atone, if he kills another גר תושב, ger toshav, the
עיר מקלט ir miklat is open for him to. רגע, Rega, גמרא
Gemara raises a contradiction now to what we were just taught. ורמינהי:
U-reminhi: לפיכך גר ועובד כוכבים שהרגו נהרגין. Lefichach ger ve-oved kochavim she-haregu
neheragin.
We have a teaching that a גר ger and an עובד כוכבים,
oved kochavim, like the non-Jews, if they kill another person, they get
punishment—they get the death penalty. קתני גר דומיה דעובד כוכבים. Katani ger
dumya de-oved kochavim. So in that case the גר ger is like
the עובד כוכבים. oved kochavim. Like you
know
we don't know what to do with him. Which way is he
going? Is he considered because of the Noahide and because of him
living in the land, is he considered a ישראל Yisrael and therefore
he gets all the same benefits and consequences or is he considered
like a non-Jew? Which category is he
going? מה עובד כוכבים לא שנא דקטל בר מיניה ולא שנא דקטל
דלאו בר מיניה. Ma oved kochavim lo shna de-katal bar minei velo
shna de-katal de-lav bar minei. It doesn't matter to us with the
עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, like where did you come up with this
that if he kills a ישראל Yisrael he gets a different punishment
and if he kills his own kind he gets a different punishment.
The עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, it doesn't matter to us who he
killed, he's going to be punished by death. So the גר ger
also should be
אף גר לא שנא דקטל בר מיניה ולא שנא דקטל דלאו בר
מיניה, af ger lo shna de-katal bar minei velo shna de-katal de-lav
bar minei, he should be killed. So
but still, we excluded the גר תושב ger toshav in the משנה,
Mishna, right? So how do we, how do we understand it? אמר
רב חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: לא קשיא. la kashya. I like that
they never have a problem with
anything.
לא קשיא. la kashya. One second, my spot, לא קשיא. la kashya.
כאן שהרגו דרך ירידה כאן שהרגו דרך עליה. Kan she-harago derech yerida,
kan she-harago derech aliya. If I understand this correctly, to kill somebody
in a downward way or to kill somebody in an upward way.
What does it mean? So to kill somebody by dropping a something
on them, a barrel, a stone, a whatever, that's considered less...
Maybe potentially less intentional. It's like, 'Oops, I dropped the barrel, somebody
happened to come walk under it,' as opposed to, 'I unintentionally threw
the knife to the other side of the mountain and it's hit
somebody.' Okay. דרך ירידה דישראל גלי איהו נמי סגי ליה
בגלות. derech yeridah de-Yisrael gali ihu nami sagi leih be-galut. דרך עליה
דישראל
פטור איהו נהרג. derech aliyah de-Yisrael patur ihu neherag. Maybe. So okay,
wait a second, did I skip a line? Maybe, maybe. כאן שהרגו
דרך ירידה וכאן שהרגו דרך ירידה. kan she-hargo derech yeridah ve-kan she-hargo
derech yeridah. דרך ירידה דישראל גלי איהו נמי סגי ליה בגלות. derech
yeridah de-Yisrael gali ihu nami sagi leih be-galut. דרך עליה
דישראל פטור, derech aliyah de-Yisrael patur, פטור, פטור, הפוך. patur, patur, afoch.
פטור patur means that it is פטור patur from the גלות, galut,
but he can get punished. So he's not פטור, patur, he goes
free, but פטור patur is he's going to be executed. Okay, פטור
איהו נהרג. patur ihu neherag. אמר לו רבא, amar lo Rava, okay,
so Rava is trying to
solve it again. Yeah, but I don't understand that. So if a
Jew kills somebody דרך עליה, derech aliyah, you're פטור, patur, so therefore
you kill the גר תושב? ger toshav? You say he should be
let off with גלות, galut, not killed. Okay, so I mean like
the discussion is what it is because it's so convoluted and so
complicated, not because it's simple. There are simplest things coming up, which
I'd love to get to, but nobody understands if you, we said
before, if you're מכהו פחות משוה פרוטה, makehu pahot mi-shaveh perutah, then
you get מלקות, malkut, which then means if you're מכהו השוה פרוטה,
makehu hashaveh perutah, what will you do? Just pay, right? I guess.
So it's much better then to hit him
more, right? Instead of then why would we want thirty-nine lashes? Just
hit him again and just pay like a dollar. Well, we had
this earlier, like okay, we had this earlier. If somebody kills somebody
by mistake, he has to be exiled to the עיר מקלט. ir
miklat. Okay, or he runs away to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat.
What if he killed somebody intentionally but there was only one witness,
or there was no התראה? hatra'ah? Then he goes away free. He
might as well come back and say, 'No, no, I actually meant
to kill him' because then he doesn't have to exile.
לגואל הדם? le-goel hadam? Huh?
If he can't kill a לגואל הדם? goel hadam? Then he's scared
that he'll be killed, but in this case... okay, but like so
you see that the גמרא Gemara like tries to work these statements
along with the פסוקים pesukim and it's like trying to, 'If this,
then this, then this, then this. Oops, we hit a wall, this
does not make sense. Okay, let's back out. How much can we
back out? Let's go a different route.' You know what? I don't
get it. Moving on. That's kind of how we're reaching not innocuous,
it's just that the, you know, the פסוקים pesukim of the תורה.
Torah. Yeah, but why? They would be pretty straightforward. I don't know,
I mean until you see, it seems to be creating scaffolding that
doesn't hold weight. The גמרא Gemara is the one that's making all
the problems. Okay, so how, this would be a fascinating, I would
love to do this as an exercise,
that we would take the פסוקים pesukim and we would be the
גמרא Gemara and we would try to figure out where it's going,
right? So we would have two conflicting פסוקים. pesukim. One says what
we read from both of them in Numbers, right? So in במדבר.
Bamidbar. One says the ערי מקלט arei miklat is to you ולגר
ולתושב, ve-la-ger ve-la-toshav, right? So
to
some sort of an everybody. And one says the ערי מקלט arei
miklat is just to you.
What I would have said is easily just that, you know, one
is building on the other one. You and everyone else, we already
mentioned everyone else again. I don't know, you know, we have this
a lot of time. כעין רוח לכל בשר וגו', ke-ein ruach le-chol
basar ve-go, you know,
the משנה mishna leaves out a whole bunch of things at a
time. Right, they don't use every case. Exactly, except it's not a
dictatorship. So you would say there's no contradiction based on A, B,
and C, and Gloria would say no, no, no, I don't see
it this way, there's no contradiction because blah, blah, blah. And somebody
else would say well, actually whatever, something else, let's bring a third
פסוק pasuk to try to settle it. That is exactly the conversation.
It's exactly what we're doing right now. Everyone is thinking the same
thing about the לכם, lachem, which doesn't say just for Jews. That's
right. That it's broad enough that it could be referring back. See,
Gloria and I agree! I can challenge it. I will challenge it
right now because who
says, who says this פסוק pasuk ערי מקלט? arei miklat? Who instructs
who with the ערי מקלט? arei miklat?
What's the background of that פסוק? pasuk? God or Moshe
saying
to בני ישראל? Bnei Yisrael? He was not talking to the גר
תושב. ger toshav. Like this was not even in the land. How
can you say that it's לכם lachem to everybody? It's
to us.
Right, but like if it was פשיטא pshita then we wouldn't have
a גמרא Gemara and we would not be who we are. But
it's not.
Some מסורה mesorah floating around that
differentiates, which is why they're struggling to put this together. Right, right,
right, to put this together, this contradiction. Right.
If we can get through the next like whatever three little sections,
at the bottom,
at the bottom there is a good story that I think is
a good מדרש midrash for something we just read in the פרשה
parsha in the last couple weeks and we will find that hopefully
more exciting than this, no offense to anybody. No, this is very
difficult to like understand logically. Maybe the takeaway is there is no
logic here and we just have to get through it.
You know, okay, side comment,
I love doing Sudoku and I had the illusion that Sudoku has
one answer.
But there are more, when you get to the very hard Sudokus,
they have more than three answers. How's it possible? Like if the
nine is here, the one is here, the four is here, it
should be only seven here. But no. So if Sudoku can have
more than one answer, I am okay with the גמרא Gemara being
more confusing than a Sudoku. Okay, מה לאבא ולא קל וחומר הוא.
Mah lo abba vela kal vachomer hu. We just did that, right?
ומה דרך ירידת ישראל גלי איהו נמי סגי ליה בגלות דרך עליית
ישראל פטור איהו נהרג. Umah derech yeridat Yisrael gali ihu nami sagi
lei begalut derech aliyat Yisrael patur ihu neherag. Yeah. Okay. Good.
Rava said, isn't it now derived by means of the קל וחומר,
kal vachomer, right, to the contrary? We can derive exactly the opposite.
If one unintentionally kills another in a what they call downward motion,
right, in a ירידה, yerida, which is a case where the killer
was a Jew, then he would be exiled. The גר תושב ger
toshav also would be exiled and nothing more. But if he killed
in an upward motion, I'm assuming it's throwing something upward, which is
a case where the if the killer was a Jew, he would
be exempt from exile. So is he killed? Like really? Is this,
that's exactly what you're asking, right? Rather אלא אמר רבא ela amar
rava באומר מותר. beomer mutar.
So now no, the case that we're talking about is where the
גר תושב ger toshav who killed another גר תושב ger toshav thinks
it is permitted to kill the victim. I have a picture here
that, this is a very important picture, it will connect. Okay, אמר
ליה אביי amar lei abaye אומר מותר אנוסו omer mutar annuso
אמר ליה שאני אומר אומר מותר קרוב למזיד הוא. amar lei sheani
omer omer mutar karov lemezid hu.
Okay.
So
Abaye says to him, one who says that it is permitted to
kill this victim because there's some circumstances beyond his control, this is
the מותר אנוס, mutar annus, yes circumstances that are beyond his control,
or is it מותר מזיד? mutar mezid? Okay, so this is like
splitting the hairs even further. I will put them to the side
here. There is a מותר mutar that is אנוס annus and מותר
mutar that is מזיד. mezid. So even in שגגה, shegaga, even in
killing somebody mistakenly, we talked about it last time, even in killing
somebody mistakenly, there can be two options. One, I brought the example
before, one that it is in circumstances beyond his control and one
that it is there is an element that was wrong and we'll
see, wait a second, where is,
oh, on the other side. Okay.
Alright, can we רגע. rega. In the גמרא Gemara where are we
where are we, גמרא Gemara observes ואזדו לטעמייהו דאתמר כסבור בהמה ונמצא
אדם כנעני ונמצא גר תושב. veazdu letameihu deitmar kesavor behema venimtza adam
kenaani venimtza ger toshav.
So now what is the situation that is like שגגה, shegaga, right?
There could be different ways to kill somebody in the wrong way.
One is while I slapped him and I didn't know it was
gonna kill him, right, that was unintentional. But another way is to
see somebody and think that it is somebody else or something else.
Hence this beautiful glorious picture here. Does anybody know what this is?
This is from a famous book.
The book is The Little Prince. Oh, and he always draws this
picture and shows it to the adults, and what is it? It's
a hat. But the Little Prince says, no, the adults don't know
how to look at pictures. This is really a snake that swallowed
an elephant.
Okay, so this is exactly the situation we have here. כסבור בהמה
ונמצא אדם. Kasavur behemah venimtza adam. He thought he was shooting a
deer, but it was really a person with antlers. כנעני ונמצא גר
תושב. Kna'ani venimtza ger toshav. He thought he was shooting a... shooting
is the wrong word, but killing an עבד כנעני Eved Kna'ani and
it turned out that it was a גר תושב. Ger Toshav. רבה
אומר חייב אומר מותר קרוב למזיד. Rava omer chayav omer mutar karov
lemezid. Okay, so now we're discussing the splitting of the מותר.
mutar. Is he liable? Is he more responsible
or less? Like what is the situation? Is it a מזיד? mezid?
We gave the example of somebody who is drinking and driving recklessly
and then kills somebody by mistake. I didn't mean it, but there
is an element of מזיד mezid as opposed to somebody who's driving
cautiously and then somebody runs into them. Okay, so this is where
the גמרא Gemara is here.
Hold on one second. רבה אומר. Rava omer. חייב. Chayav. He's liable
to be executed as with regard to one who says that it
is permitted. His actions border on the intentional. This is the מזיד,
mezid, right? He by mistake but it was close to intentional. ורב
חסדא אומר פטור אומר מותר
אנוס הוא. VeRav Chisda omer patur omer mutar anus hu. So רב
חסדא Rav Chisda says, no, the one who says that he's permitted
to kill the victim is a victim himself of circumstance beyond his
control. It's like ignorance of the law?
Not necessarily of the law, but of a situation. It's almost like
the difference between negligence and recklessness. Yes. And what, how do we
make that difference in modern law? No, I mean, very different categories,
kinds of punishment. Okay. And like a situation, right? We can go
along with the driving. So you're driving in a, whatever, a school
zone, it's supposed to be 25, you're even going 20 or something.
Right. As opposed to, so you're driving really slow and cautious and
somebody runs into your car out of nowhere, whatever. Or you're driving
fast, recklessly in the rain after you've been drinking. This category is
opposed to that category. The מזיד mezid has... Or even let's say
the one who does who says totally ignorant of the law that
killing was permissible is not an accident.
Go for another example. Let's say you're hunting for deer, but that's
an accident. Not necessarily, if he knows there's other hunters out there
and he just sees a flash of brown, maybe he shouldn't shoot
at that point, maybe he should classify whether it's a person or...
but he still knows that killing a person is not permissible. That's
what I'm saying, the previous case here where it says person thinks
that killing is permissible, that seems to be another category. I don't
think it means that he thinks killing is permissible. רגע. Rega. רבה
Rava is going to introduce a story. We like stories. It will
help us understand and it will help us look at a story
that we maybe think we knew, but is going to come up
a little bit differently. Okay. And so רבה Rava brings us איתיביה,
Eitivei, sorry, אביי לרבא, Abaye leRava, right? He brings... Where are you?
At the bottom. Second to last? Oh, second to last, yes. Okay.
רגע. Rega. No, no, no. I'm too far. I skipped too much.
איתיביה. Eitivei. איתיביה רבא לרב חסדא. Eitivei Rava leRav Chisda. And רבה
Rava is going to bring a story into this where somebody said,
oh, I didn't know, it was by mistake, and yet the Torah
implied this person would have a death penalty had there been a
court. So if he didn't mean it, how could there have been
a death? Therefore, the מזיד mezid has an impact. Okay? Kind of
okay? All right.
Okay. איתיביה רבא לרב חסדא הנך מת על האשה אשר לקחת. Eitivei
Rava leRav Chisda Hincha met al haishah asher lakachta. What is the
case from? Anybody? First rings a bell? This is from השם Hashem
appearing at night at אבימלך's Avimelech dream, right, or vision. And השם
Hashem says to אבימלך, Avimelech, you are...
in modern Hebrew מת על, met al, it's like you're to die
for, I'm really... I'm like excited about somebody. But in תורה Torah,
*Torah* language, הנך מת hincha met, על האשה אשר לקחת *Hinnacha met
al haishah asher lakahta*. You are going to be dead, executed, presumably,
for this woman that you have taken. He taken שרה *Sarah* from
אברהם Avraham *Avraham*. Why did אבימלך Avimelech, *Avimelech* took a שרה *Sarah*
from אברהם Avraham *Avraham*? He thought it was his sister. He thought
it was his sister. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks
about that thinking of אבימלך Avimelech. *Avimelech* along with this told it
was שגגה *shgaga*. He was told. He didn't just thought. He didn't
know. Okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is doing. Probably
still rape. Probably still rape. Even though he's told? Okay, but just
because she's a sister doesn't mean you can just take her and
rape her, right? Right.
I'm so like I'm excited to tell you what's coming, but no.
Okay, okay, okay.
So this would be, okay הנך מת על האשה אשר לקחת *Hinnacha
met al haishah asher lakahta*, מאי לאו בידי אדם *mai lav bidei
adam*, like what does השם *Hashem* mean הנך מת *Hinnacha met*, right,
you're dead. He's not dead. He's not going to be dead later,
but like sort of if if there was a court, which there
wasn't, there was no בית דין *beis din*, you know, we couldn't
this,
then that maybe would be the punishment that they would have given
him. And then it says, no, בידי שמים *bidei shamayim*. No, no,
no. I mean from heaven, this is the punishment you should receive.
דיקא נמי דכתיב *di'knami dikhtiv* מחטו לי *mehato li*, cuz you transgressed
against me, right, השם *Hashem* says מחטו לי *mehato li*. ולטעמיך *u'lita'amecha*
וחטאתי לאלהים *vehatati lelohim*. Oh, we have another פסוק pasuk *pasuk* from
someone else who when he takes is on the verge, he doesn't
take, sorry, let me take this a second, on the verge of
taking another man's wife, he says I sinned to God. Who is
this? יוסף *Yosef*. יוסף *Yosef*, right. יוסף *Yosef* when he is with
Potiphar's wife, he says וחטאתי לאלהים *vehatati lelohim*. And the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is asking, לאלהים ולא לאדם *lelohim velo leadam*? What do you
mean you're about to take another man's wife, this is what you're
worried about, that you're transgressing against God and not a man? אלא
דינו מסור לאדם *ella dino masur leadam*.
But rather than yes, the transgression ultimately is against God, but the
judgment is by people, would have been by people, right, had we
had the whole system. הכא נמי *hacha nami* also here for אבימלך
Avimelech, *Avimelech*, דינו מסור לאדם *dino masur leadam*.
His judgment is given to a person. This is רגע *rega*, רגע
*rega*, רגע *rega*. איתיבי *etivei*, so another objection to this opinion, right,
that was just brought, that רבא *Rava* has just raised. אביי *Abaye*
says, but look, אבימלך Avimelech *Avimelech* says, הגוי גם צדיק תהרג *hagoy
gam tzadik taharog*. And God did not object. אבימלך Avimelech, *Avimelech* said
אבימלך Avimelech *Avimelech* said, really? Okay, השם *Hashem* said אתה מת על
האשה *ata met al haishah*, you're going to be executed on account
of this woman, and אבימלך Avimelech *Avimelech* said הגוי גם צדיק תהרג
*hagoy gam tzadik taharog*, are you killing a nation that is like
צדיק *tzadik*? And he wasn't killed. So therefore, we could understand that
השם *Hashem* agrees with אבימלך Avimelech *Avimelech* that he's a צדיק *tzadik*,
right?
But no. No. What השם *Hashem* says to him, כדאמרן ואהדרה עילויה
*kedamran veahadrah ilavei*. You need to return her because the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* afterwards says, ועתה השב אשת האיש כי נביא הוא navi hu.
*ve'atah hashev eshet ha'ish ki navi hu*. Okay, now you must return
the wife to her husband because he's a prophet. גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
immediately is going to challenge this. אשת נביא הוא דתיהדר דלאו נביא
לא תיהדר *eshet navi hu dit'hadar, delav navi lo tid'hadar*? What what
wait a second, תורה *Torah*, you just said to me return the
woman because כי *ki*, but כי *ki* is not always because, but
let us go with the because in order to cause trouble, because
it's a wife of a prophet? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* challenges
it. Wait a second, you mean return the wife because she's a
wife of a prophet? Had she been a wife of anybody else,
you would have not had to return her? Of course you would
have had to return her. It's rhetoric. That is not the point
here. It also doesn't help us answer our שגגה *shgaga*. אלא כדאמר
רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן *ella kedamar Rav Shmuel bar
Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan*, הכי קאמר ליה *hachi ka'amar lei*. This is
what השם *Hashem* said to אבימלך Avimelech. *Avimelech*. ועתה השב אשת האיש
*ve'atah hashev eshet haish*, now
return the wife of this man. מכל מקום *mikol makom*, in any
case you have to return her. ודקאמרת *ve'de'ka'amart* הגוי גם צדיק תהרג
*hagoy gam tzadik taharog*? The fact that you about this other thing
that you said that you're so righteous, let me challenge a little
bit your righteousness. הלא הוא אמר לי אחתי היא *halo hu amar
li achoti hi*. אחותי היא, etcetera, right?
You, אבימלך, Avimelech are saying to me, this would be so good
to act out this conversation between God and אבימלך. Avimelech אבימלך, Avimelech.
you said, "Oh, he told me she's his sister. I did not
know." Remember, we're back in this. Like, was this intentional or was
there circumstances beyond his control? Oh look, I didn't know. Right, and
that the גמרא says נביא הוא. So that is a second part
of the פסוק pasuk that he is a prophet.
וממך
למד. umimecha lamad. אברהם Avraham is not because he's a prophet you
return it, but also in this situation, he was a prophet because
he learned from you אבימלך Avimelech, what your real intentions are. אכסנאי
הוא שבא לעיר על עסקי אכילה ושתיה שואלין אותו. achsanai hu sheba
lair al iskei achila ushtiya shoalin oto. When you come to be
a guest in an inn somewhere, the innkeeper, the host, should say
to you, "How are you? Would you like to eat? Would you
like to drink?" Right? על עסקי אכילה ושתיה שואלין אותו. al iskei
achila ushtiya shoalin oto. Ah, how was the journey?
Okay. שואלין אותו. shoalin oto. כלום שואלין אותו אשתך זו אחותך זו?
klum shoalin oto ishtecha zo achotecha zo?
Really, when you come to visit some place, you go there with
your spouse, immediately the innkeeper is like, "Mm, is that your wife?
Is that your sister?" What business is it of him? Right, he
should have been concerned with how to host his guest. And
therefore, מכאן שבן נח נהרג שהיה לו ללמוד ולא למד. mikan sheben
Noach neherag shehaya lo lilmod velo lamad. Therefore, אברהם Avraham learned from
אבימלך, that is, from אבימלך's questions, that his intentions were not clean.
And
therefore, because God says הנך מת, you are deserving of the death
penalty for doing
this, therefore, בן נח נהרג שהיה לו ללמוד ולא למד. ben Noach
neherag shehaya lo lilmod velo lamad. He should have learned by being
the בן נח ben Noach who's like the גר תושב, ger toshav,
right? He should have learned from the Jews that are living around
them, but he didn't. Okay, a little more.
This is good, I like that אבימלך unpacking that אבימלך story, that
he really learned that אברהם Avraham really learned because we also we
always read it like, "Well, but what went wrong? He asked and
אברהם Avraham answered." But there's so much, you know better than me,
there's so much that you learn from what people ask about what
they want. I think the flaw in that is that Abraham tells
Sarah before they even get there. Yeah, they're going to ask or
something and you should say. So, you know, that that's also like
a lot of it. Like, what is the subtext? You know, like
he goes to אבימלך. He knows אבימלך from before, right? It's not
their first encounter. Actually, in the תורה, אברהם is anticipating. Right, that
this is what's going to happen. But the גמרא is putting it
as אבימלך initiated it before it. But it might be that אברהם
knew this person אבימלך. Right, yeah, right. Maybe he knew that this
is the thing, you know, when people come to אבימלך, he doesn't
say "did you eat, did you drink," but he says "mm." But
then the גמרא is like sharpening it. Right, right, right. Which
we usually don't think about. Yeah, very good. Okay, another משנה Mishna
on this fabulous issue. If we can get to the bottom, that
would be super exciting. Okay. הסומא אינו גולה דברי רבי יהודה. רבי
מאיר אומר גולה. hasuma eino goleh divrei Rabbi Yehuda. Rabbi Meir omer
goleh. Okay, the blind person does not get exiled. This is according
to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says he does.
השונא אינו גולה. רבי יוסי אומר השונא נהרג מפני שהוא כמועד. hasoné
eino goleh. Rabbi Yossi omer hasoné neherag mipnei shehu kemuad. Okay, so
we have a category of a hater. And super interesting and important
to put out there, think about when we open the ארון aron
we say ויהי בנסוע הארון ויאמר משה קומה ה' ויפוצו אויביך וינוסו
משנאיך. vayehi binsoa haaron vayomer Moshe kuma Hashem veyafutzu oyvecha vayanusu mesanecha.
So in some translations the שונא soné is translated as enemy.
He's not an enemy, he's somebody who hates you.
Think about this like whatever in modern life, we might have
what do you call it, like in Congress, right, agreements with somebody
that we hate, but we have the same interests, right? As opposed
to somebody who is our enemy and is out to get us
openly. Okay, so it's slightly different category. We're not defining it here,
but it's important to note that it's not necessarily an enemy, it's
somebody that hates us. Okay.
And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says about them and we'll see in
a minute, hopefully, השונא נהרג מפני שהוא כמועד. hasoné neherag mipnei shehu
kemuad. He's like somebody who is going to do something because he
has these feelings, right? So he's already known. Yes. Can't an enemy
also work with somebody who's their enemy? Like two, you know, two
states who work together even though they're enemies because they have a
third... Well, who defines an enemy? What defines an enemy?
So an enemy has to be...
the גמרא doesn't define it. It talks about it like normal, but
it's important for us to note that it is a שונא shoneh
not an אויב. oyev. There is a word for enemy. Many translations
say שונא shoneh as an enemy. I wonder if that's a difference
that carries over into English? It might be a difference in the
Hebrew word. No, it has to, like, you know, we have
this as I said, like when we open the ארון, aron, what
do we say? יפוצו אויביך וינוסו משנאיך. Yafutzu oyvecha veyanusu mesanecha.
Your enemies will be scattered and your haters will run away. Right.
Okay, but we distinguish in that פסוק pasuk, between אויבים oyvim and
שונאים. shonim. So it's not the same. Where's this... okay, alright. And
what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is suggesting is that the שונא shoneh
is like, he doesn't need יוסי Yose either now or not... the
שונא shoneh does not need התראה hatrah because he's a שונא. shoneh.
He hates the other person, so he
is, you know, there's something in him that might cause the other
person damage because he has these feelings.
רבי שמעון אומר: יש שונא גולה ויש שונא שאינו גולה. Rabbi Shimon
omer: Yesh shoneh goleh veyesh shoneh she'eino goleh. So Rabbi Shimon says
wait, we have to distinguish between the two. Some people that hate
us, they get exile and some people don't.
שאינו גולה. She'eino goleh. זה הכלל: כל שהוא יכול לומר לדעת הרג
אינו גולה, ושלא לדעת הרג הרי זה גולה. Zeh haklal: Kol shehu
yachol lomar lada'at harag eino goleh, veshelo lada'at harag harei zeh goleh.
If there was an intentionality in the killing, he does not get
exile, he gets the death penalty. If there was no intention, שלא
לדעת, shelo lada'at, then he gets exile. Okay, גמרא is asking
where is this from? There,
we have a פסוק in this issue of the עיר מקלט ir
miklat that talks about בלא ראות. belo re'ot. Someone who...
now, something we can't translate because as soon as we translate we're
going to give it commentary. בלא ראות: Belo re'ot: without seeing who,
when, where. תנו רבנן: בלא ראות פרט לסומא דברי רבי יהודה. Tanu
Rabanan: Belo re'ot perat lesuma divrei Rabbi Yehuda. Rabbi Yehuda understands that
בלא ראות belo re'ot excludes the guy who cannot see, that he
therefore
does not get the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. But רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says בלא ראות belo re'ot דוקא davka to include the blind
person.
Two whole minutes. מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? דכתיב: אשר יבוא את רעהו
ביער. אפילו סומא אתא בלא ראות מיעטיה מיעוט. Mai ta'ama deRabbi Yehuda?
Dechtiv: Asher yavo et re'ehu baya'ar. Afilu suma ata belo re'ot mi'ateih
mi'ut.
So Rabbi Yehuda uses a different part of that פסוק, right? A
different part about the unintentional murder. It says: ואשר יבוא את רעהו
ביער לחטוב עצים ונדחה ידו בגרזן לכרות העץ ונשל הברזל מן העץ.
Va'asher yavo et re'ehu baya'ar lachtov etzim venidcha yado bagarzen lichrot ha'etz
venashal habarzel min ha'etz. So somebody who comes in the forest, he
came to whack down the trees, what do you call it? To
chop the trees. As he was doing it, oops, he was left
with the handle and the metal flew and killed somebody.
Right? And this could be even somebody that... the בלא ראות belo
re'ot is a מיעוט, mi'ut, it excludes the one that cannot see.
ורבי מאיר: בלא ראות למעט בבלי דעת למעט הוי מיעוט אחר מיעוט.
VeRabbi Meir: Belo re'ot lema'et bivli da'at lema'et havei mi'ut achar mi'ut.
Rabbi Meir says that without seeing is an exclusion and בבלי דעת
bivli da'at is another exclusion. Because we have a rule that we
don't exclude from another exclusion, then those are two separate things and
אלא אין מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא
לרבות. ela ein mi'ut achar mi'ut ela lerabbot. ורבי יהודה: בבלי דעת
פרט למתכוון ודעת. VeRabbi Yehuda: Bivli da'at perat lemitkaven veda'at. Rabbi Yehuda
says no, the בבלי דעת, bivli da'at, the one that does it
without noticing, that's like a different category. It's not one that takes
from the other, but a different category. I am very fearful I'm
going to have to stop. Yeah. You can have the other part
of the drawing for tomorrow, the issue of the two ropes. The
rope that is being cut is a mistake and the rope that
is slipping out is more intentional because otherwise he should have tied
the knot better. And with that, thank you for being with us
and a fabulous day. Thank you.